John A. Casazza Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John A. Casazza Papers 1938-2018 1970-2012
MSS86357
Casazza, John A. (John Andrew), 1924-2019
12,100 items
35 containers
13.8 linear feet
1,728 digital files (2.93 GB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Electrical engineer and educator. Correspondence, book drafts, articles, reports, printed matter, and notes in both physical and digital formats relating to Casazza's career in the electric power industry. Materials in physical formats also include photographs and clippings.
Acquisition Information
The papers of John A. Casazza were given to the Library of Congress by Casazza's daughter, Joan Fram, in 2020.
Transfers
Videocassettes and sound cassettes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the John A. Casazza Papers. Patrons are encouraged to contact the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division in advance of a research visit.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of John A. Casazza are open to research. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Access to digital content is available onsite only in the Manuscript Reading Room and requires advanced notice. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting.
Technical Requirements
Digital files were created in a Windows operation system, version unknown. Digital files in the collection include text documents in Microsoft Word 97-2003 (.doc), plain text files (.txt), and Adobe Acrobat PDF 1.4 (.pdf), presentations in Microsoft PowerPoint v.4 (.ppt), and images in Graphics Interface format v. .87a and .89a (.gif) and JPEG File Interchange format (.jpg). Digital files can be accessed with modern software or standard file viewer.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1924, Jan. 3 Born, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1941 1943 Student, Cooper Union School of Engineering, New York, N.Y.
1943 1946 Ensign, United States Navy
1945 B.E.E., Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1946 1977 Engineer; general manager, Planning and Research; and vice president, Planning and Research, Public Service Electric and Gas Co., Newark, N.J.
1949 Married Madeline Russo (died 2014)
1977 1979 Vice president, Stone and Webster Management Consultants, New York, N.Y.
1979 1998 President, chairman of the board, and board member, Casazza, Schultz & Associates, Washington, D.C.; moved in 1984 to Arlington, Va.
1990 Received Herman Halperin Electric Transmission and Distribution Award from the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)
1990 1994 Member, Energy Engineering Board of the National Research Council, Washington, D.C.
1993 Published The Development of Electric Power Transmission: The Role Played by Technology, Institutions, and People. New York: Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers
1994 Received Philip Sporn Award from the International Council on Large Electric Systems (CIGRE)
1994 2009 Founder and president, American Education Institute, Arlington, Va.; moved in 1998 to Springfield, Va.
1997 1999 Board member, Board of Adjustment, Commonwealth Edison, Chicago, Ill.
1997 2004 Outside director, Georgia Systems Operations Corporation, Tucker, Ga.
1998 2000 Member, Executive Committee of New York State Reliability Council
2000 Edited with George C. Loehr The Evolution of Electric Power Transmission Under Deregulation: Selected Readings. Piscataway, N.J.: Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers
2001 Published Sham? Shame!: Inside the Electric Power Industry. Springfield, Va.: American Education Institute
2003 Co-founder, Power Engineers Supporting Truth, Springfield, Va. Published with Frank Delea Understanding Electric Power Systems: An Overview of the Technology and the Marketplace, 1st ed. Piscataway, N.J.: IEEE Press; Hoboken, N.J.: Wiley
2007 Published Forgotten Roots: Electric Power, Profits, Democracy and a Profession. Springfield, Va.: self-published
2010 Published with Frank Delea Understanding Electric Power Systems: An Overview of the Technology, the Marketplace and Government Regulation, 2nd ed. Piscataway, N.J.: IEEE Press; Hoboken, N.J.: Wiley
2012 Published Superpower: A Historical Novel About the People Responsible for our National Power Grid. Mustang, Okla.: Tate Publishing & Enterprises, LLC
2019, Jan. 9 Died, Fairfax, Va.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John A. Casazza (1924-2019) span the years 1938-2018, with the bulk of the material dating from 1970 to 2012. The collection documents Casazza’s career in the electric power industry as an engineer, educator, and author. The papers are in English. The collection is organized into five series: Speeches and Writings File, Subject File, Course Materials, Miscellany, and Digital File.
The collection documents Casazza’s long career as an electrical engineer and business executive at Public Service Electric and Gas Company. His papers also include material related to his consulting firm, Casazza, Schultz & Associates, his teaching efforts with the American Education Institute, his advocacy work with Power Engineers Supporting Truth, and the writing of his books and other publications. Much of Casazza's work was published under the name Jack Casazza. As Casazza believed engineers and their employers have a moral responsibility to provide a service to society instead of prioritizing commercial interests, the papers frequently explore ethical issues within the electric power industry. While he advocated for engineers to have a greater role in setting electric power policy, Casazza also worked to improve the technical competence of existing government officials through educational programs.
The collection’s series are listed and briefly described below. A fuller description of each series and a list of its contents can be accessed in the series descriptions within the container list.
The Speeches and Writings File series includes book drafts, articles, reports, unpublished memoirs, and talks written by Casazza.
The Subject File series contains files on a variety of topics and issues related to the electric power industry.
The Course Materials series documents educational programs offered by Casazza, Schultz & Associates and the American Education Institute.
The Miscellany series includes correspondence, photographs, and other miscellaneous material pertaining to Casazza’s life and career.
The Digital File series contains the contents of floppy disks and CDs created and used by Casazza and overlaps with material from the other series.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged into five series:
Speeches and Writings File, 1947-2017
Subject File, 1952-2013
Course Materials, 1984-2004
Miscellany, 1938-2018
Digital File, 2000-2012
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Casazza, Jack A. (Jack Andrew), 1924-2019. Jack A. Casazza papers.; Casazza, John A. (John Andrew), 1924-2019.; Casazza, John A. (John Andrew), 1924-2019. Understanding electric power systems: an overview of the technology, the marketplace, and government regulation.; Swidler, Joseph C. (Joseph Charles), 1907-1997. Power and the public interest: the memoirs of Joseph C. Swidler. 2002.
Organizations
American Education Institute (Springfield, Va.); Casazza, Schultz & Associates.; Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers.; Power Engineers Supporting Truth.; Public Service Electric and Gas Company.; United States. Federal Energy Regulatory Commission.; United States. Federal Power Commission. National Power Survey.
Subjects
Electric industries--Moral and ethical aspects.; Electric industries--Prices--United States.; Electric industries--United States--History.; Electric industries--United States.; Electric power failures--Northeastern States.; Electric power failures--United States.; Electric power systems--Deregulation--United States.; Electric power systems--Design and construction--United States.; Electric power systems--Reliability--United States.; Electric power systems--Security measures--United States.; Electric power systems--United States.; Electric power transmission--United States.; Electric power--United States.; Electric utilities--Environmental aspects--United States.; Electric utilities--United States.; Electrical engineering--Moral and ethical aspects.; Electrical engineering--Societies, etc.; Electrical engineering--Study and teaching.; Electrical engineering.; Energy industries--Deregulation--United States.; Energy industries--Government policy--United States.; Energy industries--Law and legislation--United States.; Energy industries--Moral and ethical aspects.; Energy industries--United States.; Energy policy--United States.; Power resources--Moral and ethical aspects.; Power resources--United States.
Titles
Jack A. Casazza papers
Occupations
Educators.; Electrical engineers.
Container List
- Speeches and Writings File, 1947-2017 (Box 1-17)
  The Speeches and Writings File series includes book drafts, articles, reports, unpublished memoirs, and talks written by Casazza. The series contains drafts of several books by Casazza, including the first edition of Understanding Electric Power Systems. Research materials, correspondence, reviews, and copies of figures and illustrations are also present for some of his books. The chronological file in this series contains copies of Casazza’s professional articles, conference talks, reports, lectures, and expert testimonies given before the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and various congressional committees. Casazza collected these materials in a set of twelve binders, assigned each binder a number (i.e. “Book I”), and created separate indexes for the contents of each binder. The container list maintains his original organization of these materials. A complete index of all twelve “Books” is included at the end of the chronological file. Additional articles and reports not part of the chronological file are listed individually in the container list. Some articles explore Casazza’s personal views on topics like race relations and religion. The series also contains copies of Casazza’s unpublished memoirs and a collection of writings he identified as his most important works. This series also includes a selection of writings by others that feature Casazza's annotations. For the most heavily annotated books, the entire book was retained. In other cases, only the relevant pages were photocopied. Also present is a draft of former Federal Power Commission chairman Joseph C. Swidler’s autobiography. After Swidler's death, an edited version of this autobiography was published as Power and the Public Interest: The Memoirs of Joseph C. Swidler.
  Material types include book drafts, articles, reports, correspondence, notes, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of writing or material.
  - Articles (Box 1)
    - "The Bribing of the 'Me Now' Generation or Why We Need a Bill of Obligations," 1998 (Box 1)
    - Excerpt from Our Cooper Stories, 2016 (Box 1)
    - "Friends from Other Countries," undated (Box 1)
    - "Our Schools Promote the 'Zero Religion'," 1994 (Box 1)
    - "Riots and People: Robert and What I Learned from Him," undated (Box 1)
    - "Technical Competence, Engineering Leadership, and Electric Power," 1991 (Box 1)
    - "Understanding and Helping Other People," 2017 (Box 1)
    - "Why R and D?" 1975 (Box 1)
  - Books (Box 1)
    - The Development of Electric Power Transmission: The Role Played by Technology, Institutions, and People (Box 1)
      - Drafts, 1991-1993, (3 folders) (Box 1)
      - Publicity, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Forgotten Roots: Electric Power, Profits, Democracy, and a Profession (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 2010-2011 (Box 1)
      - Final draft, 2007 (Box 1)
      - Illustrations, 1981, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
      - Research materials (Box 1)
        - Act 1: Overture, 2005 (Box 1)
        - Act 2: The Young Industry, 1984-2007 (Box 1)
        - Act 2: The Young Industry, 1984-2007 (Box 2)
        - Act 3: The Golden Age, 1962-2005 (Box 2)
        - Act 4: The Changing World, 1978-2006, (3 folders) (Box 2)
        - Act 5: The Mortal Sin of "Profits Now," 1988-2006 (Box 2)
        - Act 6: Turbulence: The Changing Electric Power Industry Structure, 1977-2006, (2 folders) (Box 2)
        - Act 6: Turbulence: The Changing Electric Power Industry Structure, 1977-2006, (6 folders) (Box 3)
        - Act 6: Turbulence: The Changing Electric Power Industry Structure, 1977-2006, (2 folders) (Box 4)
        - Act 7: Democracy in a Highly Technical World, 1987-1993, 2000-2006, (2 folders) (Box 4)
        - Act 8: The Electric Power Engineer and His Professional Society, 1974-2006, (4 folders) (Box 4)
        - Act 8: The Electric Power Engineer and His Professional Society, 1974-2006, (6 folders) (Box 5)
        - Act 8: The Electric Power Engineer and His Professional Society, 1974-2006, (7 folders) (Box 6)
    - Sham? Shame!: Inside the Electric Power Industry (Box 7)
      - Cover art, 2001 (Box 7)
      - Final draft, 2001, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Superpower: A Historical Novel About the People Responsible for our National Power Grid (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 1978, 1991, 2007-2013, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Drafts and copy of book, 2012 (Box 7)
      - Research materials, 1968, 1982, 1991, 2007-2011, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Understanding Electric Power Systems (Box 7)
      - Figures, 2003 (Box 7)
      - First edition draft, 2003, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - First edition final draft, 2003, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - Publicity, 2002-2003, 2010 (Box 8)
      - Reviews, 2004-2009 (Box 8)
  - Chronological file (Box 8)
    - Book I, 1954-1973, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Book I, 1954-1973 (Box 9)
    - Book II, 1973-1975, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Book III, 1974-1980, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Book III, 1974-1980 (Box 10)
    - Book IV, 1956-1995, (6 folders) (Box 10)
    - Book V, 1987-1990, (4 folders) (Box 11)
    - Book VI, 1991, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Book VII, 1992-1994 (Box 11)
    - Book VII, 1992-1994, (4 folders) (Box 12)
    - Book VIII, 1994-1998, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Book IX, 1998-2002 (Box 12)
    - Book IX, 1998-2002, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Book X, 2001-2004, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Book XI, 2004-2005, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Book XII, 2007 (Box 13)
    - Index, circa 2007 (Box 13)
  - Memoirs (Box 14)
    - "My Personal and Professional Life," 2010, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - "Supplement to Personal and Professional Life of Jack Casazza," 2011 (Box 14)
  - "Most Important Writings of Jack Casazza," binder, 1964-2007, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Reports (Box 15)
    - "CIGRE Glossary of Terms Used in the Electricity Supply Industry," 2002 (Box 15)
    - "Concepts and Principles of Wheeling Among Interconnected Electric Utilities," 1990 (Box 15)
    - "History of the U.S. National Committee of CIGRE," 2007 (Box 15)
    - "How New Competitive Mechanisms Can Affect Electric System Reliability," 1997 (Box 15)
    - "Investigation of 1996 Western Area Cascading Outages Contributions from New Institutional Structures," 1996 See also Container 21, Western North America blackouts (Box 15)
    - "Keeping the Power Flowing: Ensuring a Strong Transmission System to Support Consumer Needs for Cost-Effectiveness, Security, and Reliability," 2005 (Box 15)
    - Public Service Electric and Gas Co. reports, binder, 1947, 1953-1955, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Public Service Electric and Gas Co. reports, binder, 1947, 1953-1955 (Box 16)
    - "United States/Mexico Electricity Exchanges," 1980 (Box 16)
  - Writings by others (Box 16)
    - Adventures in Public Administration: Memoirs of Joseph C. Swidler, draft, 1997, (4 folders) (Box 16)
    - Adventures in Public Administration: Memoirs of Joseph C. Swidler, draft, 1997 (Box 17)
    - Articles by Joseph Swidler, 1980-1991 (Box 17)
    - Electromagnetism and the Sacred: At the Frontier of Spirit and Matter by Lawrence W. Fagg, 1999 See also Container 22, "Living fields" theory (Box 17)
    - Energy: A Crisis in Power by John Holdren and Philip Herrera, excerpts, 1972 (Box 17)
    - Ethics and Profits: The Crisis of Confidence in American Business by Leonard Silk and David Vogel, excerpts, 1976 (Box 17)
    - The Existential Pleasures of Engineering by Samuel C. Florman, 1976 (Box 17)
    - The Hype about Hydrogen: Fact and Fiction in the Race to Save the Climate by Joseph J. Romm, excerpts, 2004 (Box 17)
    - "The Limits to Growth: A Report for the Club of Rome's Project on the Predicament of Mankind," 1972 (Box 17)
    - Power and the Public Interest: The Memoirs of Joseph C. Swidler, edited by A. Scott Henderson, excerpts, 2002 (Box 17)
    - Power Play: The Fight to Control the World's Electricity by Sharon Beder, excerpts, 2003 (Box 17)
    - Power to the People: Electric Power Deregulation an Exposé by Jack Duckworth, excerpts, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Selections from American Poetry, edited by Frederick Houk Law, 1915 (Box 17)
    - The Social Organization of Electric Power Supply in Modern Societies by Philip Sporn, 1971 (Box 17)
- Subject File, 1952-2013 (Box 17-26)
  The Subject File series contains files on a variety of topics and issues related to the electric power industry. Topics include transmission capacity, federal energy legislation, major electric power failures, and the environmental impact of utility companies. The files on national power surveys document the Federal Power Commission's 1964 survey and Casazza’s advocacy for an updated survey during the early 2000s. Also of interest are the files on the Northeast blackout of 2003. Casazza formed Power Engineers Supporting Truth (PEST) with Frank Delea, George C. Loehr, and Raymond Maliszewski in response to this event. PEST criticized the federal government’s investigation of the blackout, expressed concern about the impact of government deregulation on the North American electric power system, and looked to prevent future power failures from occurring. A small portion of the Subject File documents Casazza’s interest in connections between science and religion.
  Material types include reports, articles, correspondence, printed matter, notes, and clippings.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Catholics and Muslims, 2008 (Box 17)
  - Electric and gas rates, 1970-1972, (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - Electric power failures (Box 18)
    - Auckland, New Zealand, 1998 (Box 18)
    - Blackout History Project, 2000 (Box 18)
    - Commonwealth Edison, 1995-1999, (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - Consolidated Edison Co., 1977-1978 (Box 19)
    - Consolidated Edison Co., 2000-2006 (Box 19)
    - Eastern Pennsylvania-New Jersey-Maryland Interconnection, 1967-1968, (4 folders) (Box 19)
    - France, 1978-1979, 2004 (Box 19)
    - Georgia, 1999 (Box 20)
    - Hawaii, 1996 (Box 20)
    - International blackouts, general, 2000-2001 (Box 20)
    - Italy, 2003 (Box 20)
    - Japan, 1989-1995 (Box 20)
    - London, England, 2003 (Box 20)
    - Mid-Atlantic Power Pathway, circa 1998 (Box 20)
    - Northeast blackout, 2003-2005, (3 folders) (Box 20)
    - Northeast blackout, 2003-2005, (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - San Francisco, Calif., 1998 (Box 21)
    - South Africa, 1996-1999 (Box 21)
    - Union for the Coordination of Transmission of Electricity, 2007 (Box 21)
    - Western North America blackouts, 1989, 1996-1999, (3 folders) (Box 21)
    - Western North America blackouts, 1989, 1996-1999, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Electric utility industry structure and regulation, 1952, 1959-1975 (Box 22)
  - Energy legislation, 1972-1973 (Box 22)
  - Energy study funding, 1972-1973 (Box 22)
  - Environmental issues, 1971-1973 (Box 22)
  - Federal Power Commission, 1972 (Box 22)
  - Fusion power, 1972, 2001 (Box 22)
  - Geothermal energy, 1973 (Box 22)
  - Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers Energy Policy Committee, 2008-2013 (Box 22)
  - "Living fields" theory, 1963-2003, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Load balancing, 1973 (Box 23)
  - Load management, 1976 (Box 23)
  - Mergers of electric power companies, 1970-1972 (Box 23)
  - Mirant Corp., 2001 (Box 23)
  - Models and procedures, 1962, 1970 (Box 23)
  - National grid studies, 1971-1972 (Box 23)
  - National power surveys, 1963-1966, 1975, 1987-1993, 1999-2010, (4 folders) (Box 23)
  - National power surveys, 1963-1966, 1975, 1987-1993, 1999-2010, (4 folders) (Box 24)
  - Nuclear economics, 1972 (Box 24)
  - Nuclear fuel cycle, 1975 (Box 24)
  - Nuclear fuel management, 1970-1971 (Box 24)
  - Power industry history, 1915-1919, 1994 (Box 24)
  - Reliability methods, import and export requirements, 1970 (Box 25)
  - Research and development, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Riegel Paper Corp., 1969 (Box 25)
  - Siting problems, electric power facilities, 1970 (Box 25)
  - Sulfur dioxide, 1970 (Box 25)
  - Technological forecasting, 1970-1971 (Box 25)
  - Transmission and planning methodology in the U.S., 1975 (Box 25)
  - Transmission losses, 1954 (Box 25)
  - Underground cable developments, 1972 (Box 25)
  - Urban modeling, 1972 (Box 25)
  - Voltage reductions, 1970, 1999-2000 (Box 25)
  - Water supply, 1973 (Box 25)
  - Waste disposal, 1971-1973 (Box 25)
  - Waste disposal, 1971-1973, (2 folders) (Box 26)
- Course Materials, 1984-2004 (Box 26-33)
  The Course Materials series documents educational programs offered by Casazza, Schultz & Associates and the American Education Institute. Some programs were aimed at experienced engineers as continuing education opportunities. Others were intended for non-engineers involved in setting electric power policy, such as officials from the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and the Department of Defense. Course topics include transmission system planning and design, pricing of transmission services, causes and effects of electric power failures, electric system security, and the history of the electric power industry.
  Material types include lecture notes, course schedules, correspondence, course evaluations, and transparencies.
  Arranged alphabetically by course title or type of material.
  - Advanced Course in Electric Power Systems (Box 26)
    - Binder 1, 2000, June, (3 folders) (Box 26)
    - Binder 2, 2001, Apr., (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - Transparencies, 2001, Apr. (Box 26)
  - American Education Institute audio courses, 2001 (Box 26)
  - Blackout 101, 2004 (Box 27)
  - Blackouts and Power Shortages (Box 27)
    - Binder 1, 1999, Oct., (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Binder 2, 2000, Dec., (4 folders) (Box 27)
  - Electric Power Systems: How They Really Work (Box 28)
    - Binder 1, 1984, Oct., (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - Binder 2, 1998, Mar.-1998, Apr., (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Binder 3, 1998, Aug., (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Electric Power Systems in a Competitive Environment, binder, 1994 (Box 28)
  - Electric Power Systems in a Competitive Environment, binder, 1994, (4 folders) (Box 29)
  - Electric System Security, 2002, (2 folders) (Box 29)
  - Future Electric Transmission Systems (Box 29)
    - Binder, 2002 (Box 29)
    - Binder, 2002 (Box 30)
    - Transparencies, 2002 (Box 30)
  - Integration of Generation and Transmission, 2001, (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Introduction to Electric Power Systems, binder, 2001, (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Introductory Course in Electric Power Systems (Box 30)
    - Binder, 2000, (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Transparencies, 2000 (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous transparencies, undated (Box 31)
  - New Contractual Arrangements in a Restructured Electric Supply Industry, binder, 1996, (4 folders) (Box 31)
  - Open Access Transmission Pricing, binder, 1995, (3 folders) (Box 31)
  - Power Systems: The Basics, 1997 (Box 32)